<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An epistle to friends being a tender salutation to the faithful in God everywhere : also a letter to Charles, King of England &amp;c. / by Anne Gilman.</title>
            <author>Gilman, Anne, d. 1686.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1662</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 15 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A42775</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G768</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R28035</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">10334040</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 10334040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">44887</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A42775)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 44887)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1384:61)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An epistle to friends being a tender salutation to the faithful in God everywhere : also a letter to Charles, King of England &amp;c. / by Anne Gilman.</title>
                  <author>Gilman, Anne, d. 1686.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1662.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Harvard University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-07</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:44887:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:44887:1"/>
            <p>AN
Epiſtle to Friends;
Being a Tender
SALUTATION
To the FAITHFUL in GOD every where.
ALSO, A
LETTER
TO
<hi>CHARLES,</hi> KING of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> ANNE GILMAN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year, 1662.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:44887:2"/>
            <head>An EPISTLE to FRIENDS, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>DEar Friends, to whom this may come do I ſend
greeting. Grace, Mercy and Peace be multiplied,
in and amongſt you; who are of the Family of God,
and of the houſhold of the Faithful, in the Eternal
God of my Life doth my Soul ſalute you, who are kept in the
Faith, in which there is no ſhadow of turning: to you which
are made partakers of an endleſs Life, which is hid with Chriſt
in God, is my Life drawn; and I am even conſtrained to let
forth my Love unto you, which know the waſhing in the blood
of the Covenant, and are made partakers of an everlaſting In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance,
who have the Witneſs in your ſelves that you are
his Children; and not only Children, but Heirs, and Joynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heirs
with Chriſt: For, as we <hi>ſuffer</hi> with him, we ſhall alſo
<hi>reign</hi> with him; and though in the world we paſs through great
Tribulations, yet abiding in Him which overcomes, here is
our Peace and ſafety known: for he hath choſen us to be a
People for his Praiſe, and his Honour to dwell in; and this is
the reaſon we are called into the Vineyard, even to know the
Work and the Reward thereof: for now is the day known,
wherein the time is to be redeemed, becauſe the dayes are
evil: Therefore, dear Friends, be not ſlothful; for the Lord
is taking notice of the <hi>ſtanders idle</hi> this day: for it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red
of every one, according to your meaſures as you have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived
of the Lord, to clear your ſelves concerning this wicked
Generation: for the Beſt is let looſe out of the bottomleſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit,
and his fury is very great, becauſe he hath but a ſhort
time to reign; therefore doth he roar after his prey with a
devouring voice. Therefore, my Friends, keep upon your
watch; for this is the day wherein he is in ſubtilty transform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
himſelf into an Angel of light: But dear Lambs, keep to
that which doth diſcover him in his appearances; for that is
the Anchor you are to know, and there you are to be ſtaid,
even in the Power, over Hell and Death, for theſe are the laſt
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:44887:2"/>
enemies we are to conquer: but bleſſed be God who is mighty
in his appearance, and hath made himſelf known to be the
Captain of our Salvation, and hath diſplayed the Banner of
his Love over us, who in all our Afflictions is afflicted, and
the Angel of his preſence is known to ſupport in the time of
our need; and this is the reaſon that I am conſtrained to call
upon you to keep to your watch: and if any Lamb among you
be ſuffered to go aſtray, the Shepherd's Crook is to be known
to catch them to the Fold. Underſtand what I ſay, my Friends,
for I write to the Faithful that can reade with a ſingle heart;
who have known the Clouds paſs over, and the Vail taken a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,
and the Partition-wall broken down; even they know
what I ſay, and can feel me in the endleſs Life, and in the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſible
Fountain of Love; for herein am I united unto you;
And this is the day wherein the Lord is making up his Jewels,
therefore are we made to ſpeak oft one to another, and a Book
of Remembrance is to be written thereof: Therefore, dear
Friends, think it not ſtrange concerning the fiery Tryals,
which are to try you, as though ſome ſtrange thing happened
unto you: for, as Gold, muſt you be tryed and purified in the
fire: and this is the reaſon that he is making Veſſels fit for his
Honour to dwell in; for there is nothing can ſtand before him
but that which can endure the fire; even fire within, and fire
without. Abide it, dear Friends, and keep cloſe to the Lord;
for there is none can wear the Crown but they that endure to
the end: For the mighty God is ariſen in ſtrength, as with an
Army, to ſupport all thoſe that truſt in him, and are weak and
little in their own eyes, being kept low in his Fear; for ſuch
doth he wonderfully uphold. And here is no need of ſheltring
one under another, for the Lord is the ſhelter of thoſe that
put their truſt in him, and walk before him with an upright
heart: for it is the heart he requires, which is redeemed out
of the form, and kept ſingle to himſelf. Let them that reade,
underſtand: for this is the Key of <hi>David,</hi> which ſhutteth,
and no man openeth; and openeth, and no man ſhutteth; yea,
God Almighty it is, who is the ſtrength of all thoſe that in a
pure heart wait upon him, in the undefiled Life which keeps
blameleſs. And in an unſpotted Conſcience, the well-ſprings
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:44887:3"/>
of Life are ſet and known, which run moſt pleaſantly unto
all thoſe that fear the Lord, and walk humbly before him.
Wherefore fear not, little Flock, for it is the Father's will to
give you the Kingdom: and this is the reaſon that none of you
can be pluck'd out of the Father's hand, becauſe your Lives
are hid with Chriſt in God; and it is your meat and drink to
lie down in the Will of the Lord. And this in my meaſure am
I made a Witneſs of. And this is the reaſon that the Lord is
pleaſed to unlooſe my lips, and untye my tongue, that his
living Praiſes ſhould be ſounded forth amongſt the Heathen:
for wonderfully hath he wrought in and amongſt you; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
is his Name to be exalted above all the gods of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then:
for he is wondeful, and wondrouſly doth he work, for
the ſcattering of all that is contrary to himſelf; that whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
is ſtanding in any, that is not of himſelf, may be brought
to nothing, that his eternal living Truth may be known in
every particular. Oh you Priſoners of hope! for you do I
oft pray, and am made ſenſible of the anſwer of my Prayers,
becauſe you are kept out of the murmuring, and out of the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiring
after <hi>Egypts Fleſh-pots.</hi> Oh let the Works of the Lord
never be forgotten of you, who have taſted of his loving-kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs;
for, of his goodneſs there is no end.</p>
            <p>Therefore, my Friends, keep to that which gives you the
Victory, and keep to your Dominion, that ſin may not reign
in your mortal bodies, and here you will find peace and reſt
for your ſouls, as your minds are ſingly ſtaied upon the Lord;
and your eyes kept in your head <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> Then will there
be a watching over one another in love, and in the ſpirit of
meekneſs, as becometh Saints who fear the Lord, and give
glory to his Name: Such cannot watch with an evil eye, but
are made to watch againſt that, becauſe it is for Judgment.
So to the <hi>hidden Word in the heart</hi> do I commend you, which
gives victory over all that which ariſes contrary to it ſelf,
that noble Warriors you may be over all Corruptions and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
Luſts; for you are to triumph over all that which is
contrary to the Lord, and then all things will work together
for good: and nothing it is can ſeparate you from the Love
of God, which is made known to you that abide in his Fear;
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:44887:3"/>
which Fear is the beginning of Wiſdom; and as we abide
herein, we meet together as Children of one birth, and are
refreſhed in one banqueting-houſe of his loving-kindneſs:
and here is no vain jangling, but all agree together, and can
lie down in the Counſel of the Lord; and as we are kept to
this, there is no place for the Enemy to enter. Oh, dear
Friends, did our Enemies but know what we injoy, who are
gathered into Faithfulneſs, ſurely they would ceaſe Perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
and own their Condemnation, concerning us; but it is
hid from their eyes, and therefore can we ſay, <hi>Father, forgive
them,</hi> becauſe our love runs to our Enemies: For we who
have been made partakers of the large Love of the Lord, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
that all might have part with us in his Fear: But alas,
alas! our lamentation is taken up for them who flight theſe
precious enjoyments; but to us is he riſen with healing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
his wings, and therefore can we thankfully take the Cup
of Salvation, and praiſe the Lord amongſt the Heathen: and
this is the large Love of our God, and it is marvelous in our
eyes. O Praiſes, Praiſes, Glory and Honour be given to
God, who worketh all our works in us, and for us.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>And here I am your Fellow-labourer
in the Vineyard of our Lord.
<hi>ANNE GILMAN.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:44887:4"/>
            <head>A LETTER to CHARLES, KING of
ENGLAND, &amp;c.</head>
            <p>INcline thine ear (O King) and ſlight not the precious
Warnings of the Lord, which daily are made known unto
thee, by that of God in thy own Conſcience; and large and
many have been the Warnings of the Servants of the Lord un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
thee, but they have been caſt behind thy back: And now
is our God riſen in his Mighty Power, to make Inquiſition for
innocent Blood; therefore, prepare, prepare, to meet the
Lord, and conſider what account thou canſt give of the Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent
Blood which cryes in the ears of the Lord for vengeance,
it is the voice of thy Brothers righteous blood which thou art
to give an account of this day; and this is required at thy
hands by him, who hath the hearts of Kings in his hands, and
turneth them as the rivers of waters whither he pleaſeth. What
have we done (O King) that ſuch uſuage we ſhould receive
from thy hands, and by thy orders, that Souldiers ſhould come
into our peaceable Meetings in a warlike manner, as if ſome
great enemies were to be conquered, amongſt the People of
God, whom by ſcorners are called <hi>Quakers,</hi> who cannot hold
up a weapon againſt any? I ſay, What have we done that we
ſhould be haled, many of us, out of our Meetings, and caſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
ſtinking Priſons on heaps, where, for want of air and room,
many have ſealed to this Teſtimony with their death, before
they can deny to Worſhip God as they are perſwaded in their
own Conſciences? for, if thou ſhouldeſt prepare, in the room
of Priſons, a fiery Furnace, or a Lions den, we can as conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tedly
lye down, in the Will of our God, as we can ſuffer our
bodies to lye in Priſon: For the ſame Law which took hold of
the Saints of God in the dayes of old, doth take hold of us at
this day: for we cannot bow to the imaginations of men con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning
the Worſhip of our God. And before we can own any
man to be our Teacher, we can ſuffer death: for our Life can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
be taken away, it is hid with Chriſt in God; for thoſe that
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:44887:4"/>
will live godly in Chriſt Jeſus, muſt ſuffer Perſecution: And
therefore (O King) we are not careful to anſwer thee in this
matter, for our Confidence is in the Lord, and our Strength
lieth in him, who is God Almighty, and doth ſave his People
from their ſins, and from the wrath of our Enemies; and he
giveth us courage and boldneſs, ſo that our lives, or any
thing we do enjoy, is not near or dear unto us, for our Wills
are freely given up into the hands of the Lord, that he ſhould
do with us as ſeemeth good in his fight; for this I know, that
all things ſhall work together for good to thoſe that love God,
and are called for this purpoſe to ſuffer for his Names ſake,
who comes through great Tribulations, their Garments are
waſhed in the Bloud of the Lamb. And this is the Reaſon
we cannot Conform to the Idol ſhepherds, which preach for
Money, and divine for Hire, and ſeek their Gain from their
Quarters; our Souls abhor ſuch Teachers, for we are Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed
from their mouths; and we ſhould know it to be a
yoke of bondage, to turn to them again. And be it known
unto thee (O King) that the Lord is riſen, who is the Migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
God of <hi>Jacob,</hi> in ſtrength, as with an Army, and is ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tering
to pieces all the deceitful workers of Iniquity; for
though his loving kindneſs hath been plentifully known
amongſt his People, yet this will not excuſe thee, when the
great God ſhall render unto every one according to the deeds
done in the body; and though God is pleaſed to preſerve his
People in the hollow of his Hand, and hide them under his
Pavillion; becauſe his hand is not ſhortened, but his arm is
ſtretched forth ſtill, becauſe to us he is known a Deliverer in
the time of trouble, therefore can we ſtand ſtill and ſee his
Salvation.</p>
            <p>And therefore am I bold to declare, That the Lord is riſen
for the Redemption of his People, and is making way for his
ranſomed Ones to paſs over; but <hi>Pharaoh</hi> and his Hoſt are to
be caſt into the Sea of God's wrath: for thoſe that fear the
Lord, are his Promiſes made known unto, and his Secrets are
made known to thoſe that fear his Name; but to the proud,
and haughty, and to thoſe that forget God, and turn their
backs at his Reproof, and will none of his Counſel, ſuch will
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:44887:5"/>
our God ſweep away with the beeſom of deſtruction; for the
worker of Iniquity will not be able to abide his Preſence in
that day: Therefore (O King) conſider what thou art doing,
for the Lord hath long waited upon thee to be gracious, and
many precious Warnings have been handed to thee through
the Servants of the Lord; yet that doth not clear me in the
ſight of my God: therefore (O King) return, return, and
repent, and harden not thy heart, as in the day of provocati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
againſt that ſecret witneſs of God, which reproves thee ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly
when no mortal eye ſeeth. Therefore, if they were to
be caſt into utter darkneſs, who did not viſite the Servants of
the Lord, and who did not cloath them, and who did not feed
them when they were in Priſon; what will become of thoſe
who caſt them into Priſon, and cauſe them to go hungry
through their hot Perſecution? I ſay, it were better for a mill<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone
to be hanged about their necks, and they caſt into the
midſt of the Sea, than that they ſhould offend one of the little
ones that put their truſt in the Lord. Therefore (O King)
lay it to heart, for theſe Warnings are not come forth in vain;
for to that of God in thy Conſcience do I defer my Cauſe,
and let it plead for us when we are out of ſight: for if Fire
ſhould be for us prepared, the aſhes of our bones would riſe
as a witneſs againſt thee to plead the innocency of our Cauſe
before thee. Therefore in love to thy Soul are theſe lines
given forth, that a ſtop may be put to the Perſecution of the
Saints; And ſo whether thou wilt hear or forbear, I have
cleared my ſelf in the ſight of my God concerning thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <signed>ANNE GILMAN.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:44887:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
